<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"> <id>https://jexxers.github.io/</id><title>Thoughtlot</title><subtitle>Life. Tech. Reflections.</subtitle> <updated>2022-07-22T07:38:05-04:00</updated> <author> <name>Jess Leung</name> <uri>https://jexxers.github.io/</uri> </author><link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://jexxers.github.io/feed.xml"/><link rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en-US" href="https://jexxers.github.io/"/> <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.0">Jekyll</generator> <rights> © 2022 Jess Leung </rights> <icon>/assets/img/favicons/favicon.ico</icon> <logo>/assets/img/favicons/favicon-96x96.png</logo> <entry><title>Blitzscaling by Reid Hoffman and Chris Yeh</title><link href="https://jexxers.github.io/posts/blitzscaling/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Blitzscaling by Reid Hoffman and Chris Yeh" /><published>2021-05-10T00:00:00-04:00</published> <updated>2021-05-10T00:00:00-04:00</updated> <id>https://jexxers.github.io/posts/blitzscaling/</id> <content src="https://jexxers.github.io/posts/blitzscaling/" /> <author> <name>Jess Leung</name> </author> <category term="Tech" /> <summary> We’re in an interesting period of capitalism, which to my surprise firms capture relatively miniscule amount of value it creates. Technological change is happening at breakneck speeds which are leaving people scared, uneasy and shocked. One of the very reasons I love innovation and disruption is this: People should be part of building the future, rather than feeling like the future is bei... </summary> </entry> <entry><title>The Universe is Within Us and Connects Us</title><link href="https://jexxers.github.io/posts/astounding-fact/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Universe is Within Us and Connects Us" /><published>2021-04-12T00:00:00-04:00</published> <updated>2021-05-10T19:26:12-04:00</updated> <id>https://jexxers.github.io/posts/astounding-fact/</id> <content src="https://jexxers.github.io/posts/astounding-fact/" /> <author> <name>Jess Leung</name> </author> <category term="Life" /> <summary> The most astounding fact… is the knowledge, that the atoms that compromise life on Earth, the atoms that make up the human body, are traceable to the crucible, that cooked light elements into heavy elements, in their core, under extreme temperatures and pressure. These stars, the high mass ones among them, went unstable in their later years; they collapsed and exploded, scattering their enri... </summary> </entry> <entry><title>13th, Fantastic Fungi, Crip Camp, Disclosure, The Farewell, Nomadland</title><link href="https://jexxers.github.io/posts/media/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="13th, Fantastic Fungi, Crip Camp, Disclosure, The Farewell, Nomadland" /><published>2021-03-14T00:00:00-05:00</published> <updated>2021-05-22T23:44:26-04:00</updated> <id>https://jexxers.github.io/posts/media/</id> <content src="https://jexxers.github.io/posts/media/" /> <author> <name>Jess Leung</name> </author> <category term="Life" /> <summary> 13th, prison industrial complex. Fantastic Fungi. Crip Camp. Disclosure, trans-folx in media. The Farewell, asian family lies to grandma about her death. Nomadland, the less glamorous side of vanlife. 13th by Ava DuVernay This documentary is one of the best I’ve seen in a while. The re-invention of racism is the main narrative of this documentary. The pacing of documentary is fast, and is ... </summary> </entry> <entry><title>The Undoing Project, White Fragility, Homo Deus, Shoe Dog, Changing Your Mind</title><link href="https://jexxers.github.io/posts/books/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Undoing Project, White Fragility, Homo Deus, Shoe Dog, Changing Your Mind" /><published>2021-03-14T00:00:00-05:00</published> <updated>2021-05-23T00:41:25-04:00</updated> <id>https://jexxers.github.io/posts/books/</id> <content src="https://jexxers.github.io/posts/books/" /> <author> <name>Jess Leung</name> </author> <category term="Life" /> <summary> The Undoing Project, the love story between two friends. White Fragility, how to spot racism. Homo Deus, humanity’s next frontiers. Shoe Dog, the story of Nike. How to Change Your Mind, altered states of consciousness. The Undoing Project by Michael Lewis I’ve been a big fan of Daniel Kahneman and Amos Tversky’s work, after reading Thinking Fast and Slow. This book is refreshing as it e... </summary> </entry> <entry><title>Talking to Strangers by Malcolm Gladwell</title><link href="https://jexxers.github.io/posts/talking-to-strangers/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Talking to Strangers by Malcolm Gladwell" /><published>2021-01-04T00:00:00-05:00</published> <updated>2021-05-22T23:44:26-04:00</updated> <id>https://jexxers.github.io/posts/talking-to-strangers/</id> <content src="https://jexxers.github.io/posts/talking-to-strangers/" /> <author> <name>Jess Leung</name> </author> <category term="Life" /> <summary> From the first time I spotted “The Tipping Point” at a bookstore, I was hooked. Malcolm Gladwell has an art for weaving stories and analyses of social phenomenon. His latest book, Talking to Strangers was a fun binge. On the other hand, this book covers some heavy material. The book central ideas are: truth-default theory, transparency, and coupling. Humans are likely to default-to-truth, ... </summary> </entry> </feed>
